<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Royal prophesie of David, Cardinal of France, touching the death of Charles the first by his own subjects, and establishing his issue by a monk prophesied in the reign of Philip, then King of France, and Richard the First, King of England / revived and brought to light by ... Father Edward out of the French chronicles, and applied unto these times ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57796</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8210506</idno>
  <idno type="VID">41101</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264209146</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08210506</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57796)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1238:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Royal prophesie of David, Cardinal of France, touching the death of Charles the first by his own subjects, and establishing his issue by a monk prophesied in the reign of Philip, then King of France, and Richard the First, King of England / revived and brought to light by ... Father Edward out of the French chronicles, and applied unto these times ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41101:1"/>
            <p>THE ROYAL PROPHESIE OF DAVID, Cardinal of <hi>France;</hi> Touching the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> the first, by his own Subjects; and the Establishing his Issue by a MONK.</p>
            <p>PROPHESIED In the Reign of Philip, then King of FRANCE, and RICHARD the First, King of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>REVIVED <hi>And brought to light (by a Learned Vrere, father</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) <hi>out of the</hi> French <hi>Chronicles; and applied unto these times. The most part of this PROPHESIE being already fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41101:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41101:2"/>
            <head>THE Royal Prophesie OF <hi>David,</hi> Cardinal of France, touching the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> the First, by his own Subjects, and the establishing of his Issue in after ages: Prophesied in the Reign of <hi>Philip,</hi> then King of France, and <hi>Richard</hi> the first King of <hi>England. Revived, and brought to light, by a Learned</hi> Vrere <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Edward, <hi>out of the</hi> French <hi>Chronicles, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to these very times.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ILLY,</hi> that learned Prognosticator, who is so taken up with Forreign Kings is Sand-blinde, sees far abroad (all lyes) nothing nigh, gathering but guesses, and they from the stars, whilest <hi>Endors</hi> woman and <hi>Shiptons</hi> wife, with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>David,</hi> study a higher strain.</p>
            <p>The story of <hi>Saul</hi> and the woman of <hi>Endor,</hi> and her familiar is sufficiently known, who told <hi>Saul</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41101:3"/> less then what happened. <hi>Shiptons</hi> wife told <hi>Woolsey, he mght see</hi> York, <hi>but never come to it:</hi> true enough both of them.</p>
            <p>Far greater is the wisdom, prudence, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Cardinal <hi>David,</hi> as to satisfie a King so boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly of the events that would happen for the tearm of 600 years to come; as in this Prophesie appears the greatest part to be already past, to which these times may thank that learned Vrere father <hi>Edward</hi> for his publication hereof.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of <hi>Richard Cuer de Lion,</hi> King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> or Lyons heart, and <hi>Philip,</hi> then King of France, lived one <hi>David,</hi> an Exorcist; for in the <hi>Romish</hi> Religion they have Cardinals, who are the Popes Senators, or Councellors. Now a Cardinal is derived from <hi>Cardo,</hi> the hinge of a door, because on them (a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the door on its hinges) all weighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church are turned.</p>
            <p>Of these Cardinals are seven orders, to wit, Door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Readers, Exorcists, Acoliths, or Taper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, Sub-deacons, Deacons, and Priests.</p>
            <p>A Cardinal of the third order was this <hi>David,</hi> whose Office was to call on the name of Jesus, and by that Name to adjure the unclean spirits to depart out of the possessed, on whom h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laid his hands; when the Exorcist is ordained, he receiveth the book of adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations from the Bishop or Pope, saying; <hi>Take and learn these by heart, and receive power to lay thy hands on the possessed, whether he be Baptized, or a Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus as yet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> weary of King <hi>Richard</hi>'s company, not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41101:3"/> able to bear the Honour done to that Mighty Prince; envying his High Fortunes at the Holy Land in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia, when <hi>Tanchred</hi> the Usurping King, gave King <hi>Richard</hi> 6000 Ounces of Gold in Cyprus, and in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, formerly called Ptolemais, where <hi>Philip</hi> King of France redeemed a thousand and five hundred Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians that were then in bondage, and so left King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> returned into his own Countrey; and sending for this <hi>David,</hi> desirous to know the success of King <hi>Richard</hi> before hand, and what should happen to that linage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> first, as the story sayes, reads these words; <hi>Coeli <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>narrant gloriam Dei fortis, &amp; opus manuum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus indicat expansum eorum. Dies ad diem eructat ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem &amp; nox ad noctem ostendit scientiam. Post dixit Deus sunto Luminaria in expanso Coeli, ad distinctionem faciendum inter diem &amp; noctem, ut sinit in signa cum tempestatibus, tum diebus &amp; annis, &amp;c.</hi> After a pause, sighing, he said; <hi>O unfortunate fortunate Prince! Whose cheifest honours abide in his misfortunes, King</hi> Richard <hi>shall add honour to honour, until he ascend (with a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from a wing) from the reach of envy; his Issue shall never reign, he himself shall suddenly be a priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet not long so remain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifth Kings Reign after him, shall <hi>France</hi> in a manner be conquered, but shall not long so abide, it shall return to its pristine condition; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing shall be a scourge to <hi>France,</hi> and shall not be without a King till he come, whose father treading the <hi>Thistle,</hi> shall snatch at the <hi>Rose,</hi> and joyning them together in his own hand, shall deliver them to his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41101:4"/> Sons hand, where they shall there wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; so that, that second sons Issue shall lay hold on the Thistle and wholly grasp it, thereby thinking to recover the Rose, but it shall not then be; for his Father, whose name shall begin with an hundred, shall be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and depapitated by one whose name shall begin with the same letter, and he for a small season shall Tyrannize over them that installed him, by cropping off the Head of Thistle and Rose; Yet immediately after, shall the people earnestly long after the Issue Banished, who shall not be restored to his Fathers Dignity, until a MONK come from the Hybernian Isles in power, and have traversed the hory headed NEPTUNE, Conquering the Eagle, and ruling sole Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch over the Ocean; who shall freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe up his power to the Tyrant of those times, and return to his Northern station, where he shall quietly rest, until the half hundred come, one whose name shall so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, who shall strive to withstand the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, another sir-name so beginning, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41101:4"/> shall not be able; for he whose strength is as a thousand, whose wisdome is far beyond the Serpents, having the whole Thistle shall gather the Rose and Joyn it to the Thistle, and deliver it to the Lions Whelp, after which time shall arise and go round the World a MONK leading a Lyon by the paw, with a Thistle and a Rose, presenting to him, and they shall go and gather up the Lily and joyn it to them and shall so continue for three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years.</p>
            <p>All which spoken and ended, <hi>Philip,</hi> the French King then went pensive away, at which time <hi>David</hi> writ these Verses.
<q>
                  <l>In the eight Kings reign <hi>Englands</hi> race shall cease,</l>
                  <l>And to the second turn to have a setled peace,</l>
                  <l>Which in the second, <hi>King</hi> shall for a while decay,</l>
                  <l>Yet by a <hi>MONK</hi> his Issue <hi>Banisht</hi> shall have sway;</l>
                  <l>And then the <hi>Lilly, Thistle, Rose,</hi> in one shall joyn</l>
                  <l>And subvert all, that shall against them combine,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>160</hi> Fore fathers shall have left</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Country,</hi> then their Son of it shall be bereft</l>
                  <l>And put to flight, until a valiant warlike <hi>Monk</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>shall come and help—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Nobis haec invicta miserunt 160 proavi. Tum &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41101:5"/>
               <head>The Prophesie explained.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CHARLES</hi> Mighty Monarch did the <hi>C</hi> begin,</l>
                  <l>After whose Death, <hi>Usurping C.</hi> came in;</l>
                  <l>By Will and force, he some <hi>few years</hi> bore sway,</l>
                  <l>Nothing but <hi>Blood</hi> his fury could allay:</l>
                  <l>Alas this hundred, and his <hi>Crooked Race</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were like <hi>Usurpers</hi> turn'd out of the place</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Honour,</hi> as they well deserv'd indeed,</l>
                  <l>And now the <hi>L</hi> for fifty doth succeed;</l>
                  <l>Stout <hi>Neptune's</hi> left, and by the <hi>MONK</hi> so bold,</l>
                  <l>Who doth appear this <hi>Riddle</hi> to unfold.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Right</hi> shall have <hi>Right;</hi> for in a little space</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A hundred</hi> shall be of the <hi>hundreds Race.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>MONK</hi> will joyn (as all appearance shows)</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Exil'd Thistle</hi> to the <hi>Happy Rose,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who shall in peace these <hi>Nations</hi> free from fears,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Govern</hi> in safety for three hundred years.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>